Vincent Van Go, a painter who breaks the
boundaries of art. Today, his paintings
are among the most famous and most
expensive in the world.
>> For you, sir, 75 million.
>> This image of the tragic genius between
genius and madness.
>> A painter who lives with prostitutes.
>> That is a lie. who is considered a
troublemaker by his colleagues
who mutilates himself out of despair.
A very difficult person to place Vincent
Fang dies poor and misunderstood. Who
was he really? A madman or a genius with
a very vulnerable soul. Researchers are
using state-of-the-art methods to find
the real Vincent Van Go behind this
mysterious figure.
>> He has very high ambitions, very high
hopes, big dreams.
>> They want to unlock the secrets of his
art and to shed new light on the low
points of his life.
>> It's phenomenal to think that he managed
to accomplish this within a space of 10
years to become a leading member of the
Aven Guards starting from somebody that
could hardly draw. The results of
science paint a new, startlingly
different picture of this giant of art.
Here in a mental asylum, Vincent Fang
produces some of his greatest
masterpieces. The former monastery of S
Paul demo near San Rei in Province.
In May 1889, the Dutchman seeks refuge
behind its thick walls from the life
that overwhelms him.
Refuge from the people who don't
understand him.
and he hopes for help in the face of the
mysterious seizures that haunt him.
What keeps Van Go alive is his art. He
wants to, he has to keep painting.
The starry night. No one before him had
ever painted a night sky in this way.
Instead of depicting reality true to
nature, Van Go alienates and abstracts,
thus anticipating modernist painting.
In the mental asylum in San Remi,
Vincent Fang struggles with the greatest
crisis of his life. After a strange
quarrel, he mutilates his left ear.
Flurries of mental derangement keep him
from painting again and again. He eats
paint and drinks tarpentine.
Forg says that he has hallucinations
that he hears things um that he really
didn't at during those attacks that he
doesn't know what he's doing.
Fungo suspects that his feverish
creative work is partly to blame for the
seizures. He accepts them as the price
to pay for great art. He wrote to his
brother Teo, "My pictures cost me
dearly, sometimes perhaps even in blood
and brains.
In fact, Fang wears himself out painting
362 paintings in the last two years of
his life alone and he revolutionized
art.
You have to understand that what Fhawk
was making at the time was quite
out of line of everything.
The thing that he added to art and art
history is the fact that you can think
of the world as something in lines that
you see movement in his pictures and
that's something totally new.
>> But above all, Fangok depicts the world
in completely new luminous colors.
He was constantly pushing the
boundaries. So there's a kind of level
of intensity to his color in many of his
paintings that was really novel in his
time.
Since then we have Andy Warhol and Ghard
Richtor and other uh colorists who you
know played at the very edges of what
color can be. But we have to think back
what this looked like in the 1880s. It
was very shocking.
>> In his day, the verdict was that such
art cannot be the product of a healthy
mind. But this assessment is overturned
in the following decades.
>> Somehow he becomes Vincent Van Gogh, the
creator of this huge body of
masterpieces that have won over the the
the hearts and minds of the world.
>> What was his driving force? Are his
paintings the spontaneous result of his
madness or the expression of a highly
sensitive artist's soul?
Anyone who wants to understand Fang and
his gigantic will probably come closest
to him in Amsterdam.
As the world's largest collection of the
artist's work, the Van Go Museum
attracts millions of visitors year after
year. But his works are also
meticulously studied here. In order to
preserve them for posterity in the best
possible way, researchers want to
understand exactly how Van Go's
masterpieces were created and how they
were originally intended to appear.
It really started when we started to
examine each painting one by one, taking
out of its frame. Often underneath the
frames, where the paint has been
protected from light, there were
remnants of much brighter color around
the edges. The intense colors make Van
Go's sunflowers the eye catcher of every
exhibition.
What might the magically luminous still
life have looked like fresh on the
easel? That's what a unique experiment
by the museum aims to show.
The search for the secrets of Van Go's
colors begins in the laboratory of the
Imperial Cultural Heritage Office of the
Netherlands with tiny samples of the
painting. Under the microscope, the
cross-sections make layers of color that
have already faded on the surface
visible again. Fangok's very volatile
red, for example.
A mass spectrometer reveals the chemical
elements contained in each sample. These
in turn reveal the composition of the
colors and reveal the extent of the
discoloration.
But the researchers do not leave it at
that. They want to combine science and
art. Their new knowledge makes it
possible to reproduce Van Go's original
colors using old recipes from the
archive.
The aim of the project to have the
famous masterpiece copied as accurately
as possible. The museum entrusts
Charlotte Kaspers, artist and restorer,
with the task.
So that's a really strange thing about
the sunflowers actually. Everybody in
the world knows them, but the painting
already has aged. So it's it's like an
old person you get to know. Whereas it
has been just newly born when it came
from Van Go's easel and then it was
really bright. It's famous. Everybody
knows it, but not in the way um he made
it.
Charlotte Caspers has to understand the
structure of the painting in detail
before she can reconstruct it. To do
this, she uses X-ray images, color
cross-sections, so-called XRF scans, and
transmitted light photos of the
painting.
>> So, all these things combined
um yeah, give quite a good plan of of
how to start and and what to use, how to
work.
I love doing this and I always do this
with a lot of respect because it also
feels very private when you go so deep
in somebody else's work. You see what he
was looking for, searching for uh why he
made changes. Um yes, it feels very
intimate
>> for Charlott Caspers. Repainting the
sunflowers means channeling Van Go,
feeling how he was, who he was.
Vincent was born and raised in Gord
Sundat, a village in the south of
Holland. His father Teoddoris is a
strict Protestant priest. Mother Anna,
bourgeoa and status conscious, keeps her
children away from the poor peasant
children.
But the siblings have each other.
Vincent is especially close with his
little brother Teo. He invents games for
him and they explore nature together.
Vincent, see here, I found an egg.
>> Great. Take it to mama.
>> Teao is Vincent's closest confidant
throughout his life. Perhaps the only
person who ever really understood him.
>> He seems to have been to a certain
extent indeed an an a lonely boy too. I
didn't think an out an outsider.
and an oddball. Tirelessly and
meticulously, he collects, examines, and
cataloges beetles, plants, and birds
nests. He lives in his own world. He
devotes himself to things that excite
him with an almost fanatical devotion
and passion.
>> Vincent, dinner is ready.
>> Can I just finish doing something?
>> You must come down now at once.
>> No. Little Vincent often argues with his
parents and withdraws from them.
His father and his mother believed that
it was crucial for their children to
temper their speech, to temper their
emotions, and to live life in an orderly
way. And all of a sudden, they have this
child who right from the beginning
didn't conform to anything. that the
maids called him um the strange boy.
>> His whole life, Vincent's parents do not
accept that he is different and deny him
the recognition he so longs for.
At a loss as to what to make of their
strange boy, they arranged for him to
train in his uncle's art printing
empire. Vincent is 17 years old at the
time. For the first time, he finds
himself in the world of art. as a
salesman.
This only existing photo of him is taken
two years later. When Vincent is
transferred because of his rude manner
and he was shipped off to be a shipping
clerk at the at the Enterprise in
London, he was fired from that. He goes
to Paris and he insulted the clients. If
somebody was looking at a painting that
he didn't like, he would go up to them
and say only somebody with terrible
taste would be interested in that in the
enterprise he was working in. So they
not only fired him, they banished him
from ever stepping foot in the gallery
again.
>> He was a book seller. He uh he u and he
went back to London and to to England
again and there he uh worked as a
teacher in a school for very poor
salary. At that point um he basically
tried to become a missionary.
>> The Borinage Kfield in Belgium. After
his constant failure, Vincent finds work
as a lay preacher here at the age of 25.
Jesus Christ was the carpenter's son. He
worked for 30 years in a humble
workshop.
He was a laborer with marks of of of
weariness and of suffering on his face.
Just just like you who simple and proud
and believing in God enter the mind day
after day. Talk of revolution. But God
wants us to live humbly on this earth of
his. This
>> wants his congregation to live as simply
and piously as he does. His sermons are
not only muddled. However, they also
strike the wrong note. The downtrodden
miners are not comforted by Van Go's
words.
They see the young man rather as a
religious fanatic who overdo it with his
priestly existence.
He lets himself go to such an extent
that even the dusty coal miners consider
him a filthy disgrace.
Once again, Van Go fails here, too.
Despite his deeply and sincerely felt
religious vocation, it says it is here.
It's really very easy. It's It's in
here. It's It's all in here.
>> His community turns away from him. They
even ensure that he is recalled.
For Vincent, it is the lowest point of
his life so far. He is penalous,
unemployed, aimless. His decline also
disturbs his family. His own father
wants to have him committed to a mental
institution.
It gives you a sense of what the family
felt about him that they thought he
needed to be committed. I don't think it
is it takes um Sigman Freud to
understand that for many of us uh uh
trying to to live up to our parents'
expectations especially when they we we
haven't in uh done that is a very strong
motive force and it certainly was for
Vincent.
He is extremely disappointed to have
failed again, to be abandoned by
everyone again. Deeply despondent,
Vincent writes to his brother Teao.
He was searching for
a place in the world for himself.
I think he was longing to console people
but also to be consoled.
>> Together with other art historians,
Ninka Baka has analyzed the extensive
correspondence between Vincent and Teao.
The letters provide a unique glimpse
into Vincent's thoughts, plans, and
inspirations and also his spiritual
life.
Thanks to the letters, we also learn of
Theo's reaction to his brother's
despair. He responds with a proposal
that gives Vincent a new lease of life.
Teao knows his older brother likes to
draw. If Vincent would like to try his
hand as an artist, he would support him
financially.
Still in Binina, Vincent sets to work.
At the age of 27, an age when other
artists are creating masterpieces, Fang
is still painting rudimentary figures in
pencil.
Fungo is not gifted with natural talent.
But just as his tendency to excess was
disastrous in bourgeoa life, with art
his fanatical zeal will prove to be a
stroke of luck. He works tirelessly.
Can you move a little? Yes.
In the Hag he finds a deaf mute
pensioner who lets him dress him up for
a pittance.
At the time Fungo struggled with
dimensions and perspective. He therefore
made use of a perspective frame as an
aid.
In his letters to Teao, he
enthusiastically describes its
construction and function. In fact, the
self-taught artist will be dependent on
this crutch for a long time.
This is apparent in works created years
later, like this one from Mora in Paris.
The auxiliary lines are visible here
even to the naked eye.
Fan go, who stubbornly refuses a
classical artist's training, needs the
aid to convey dimensions correctly on
the canvas.
At the time, Van Go was living with Zen
Hornik, a prostitute with illegitimate
children, much to the displeasure of his
family.
Vincent knew that his parents and also
Teao were against this relationship, but
he also felt very attached to her and to
her children. This is the only time that
he actually had his own his own family.
>> Vincent gives into pressure from his
family and ends his relationship with
scene. Despite his nonconformist nature,
he longs for companionship. Yet once
again, he is alone.
5 years into his career as an artist, at
the age of 32, Fangok believes he has
finally created his first great
masterpiece, the potato eaters.
For months, he painted portraits and
made individual studies for this
picture.
As an artist, he hopes for the
recognition that is denied him as a
human being. The reactions to the
earthcoled work, however, are painful.
His brother Teao and fellow painters
considered it old-fashioned and
unsellable.
He finally enrolls at the art academy in
Anto that wants to put him in the
beginners's course.
Fangok is in danger of failing on this
classic path of a painter even at the
basic skills that are required. So how
does this amateur become one of the
greatest artists in history?
Christiey's auction house in New York in
1990 seemingly out of nowhere a painting
appears on the auctioneer stage that has
not been seen in public for decades. 25
million, 26 million, 27 million, 28
million, 29 million.
>> The famous portrait of Dr. Gashier.
Painted in 1890, it is the last major
portrait the Dutchman painted before his
death. It shows Van Go's neurologist
Paul Ferdin Gasher.
When Van Go made it, he was so poor that
he had to keep exchanging drawings and
paintings for food and paint.
Selling in the room now. All done then.
Against the telephone, not yours here.
Fair warning. At $75 million for you,
sir. 75 million.
>> $75 million.
This makes the painting the most
expensive work of art of its time. The
buyer, a Japanese businessman.
The story of Dr. Gash however is not
only one of top prices but also an art
thriller. The Stadle Museum in Frankfurt
is involved
in 2019. It celebrates Van Go as the
inspiration for the German
expressionists with an exhibition and
explains why Van Go became so popular in
Germany at the beginning of the 20th
century. The fact that Dr. The gash of
all people is missing from this
exhibition is all the more regrettable
for the museum as it had acquired the
famous portrait in 1911.
The only remnant of the famous portrait
is stored in the museum's painting depot
in the basement.
It is the original frame for Dr. Gashier
kept as a reminder of scandalous events.
that was really one of the key works
here in the collection. He was initially
presented in his pioneering role in his
role as an inspirational figure of the
German avang guard and I also think that
was part of the downfall because of
course these were the artworks that were
taken down here in the museum in 1933.
Provenence researcher Iris Schmeiser had
delved deeply into the Dr. Gashier case
file for the stad museum the national
socialist's justification for the
confiscation problematic foreigner
and with regard to the so-called
problematic foreigners that's a quote
that's really the term that was used
which also included van
there was talk of mental perversion
aberration degeneration being out of
sorts
Dr. Gashier ends up in Berlin along with
paintings by other denigrated artists.
>> They were first stored there in a
granary and then Hitler and Guts
inspected these stocks. And in this
context, we can assume that they plan to
exploit these products of decaying art
in inverted commas to make money.
And Dr. Gashi then became something like
a pilot project to try this out.
>> Marshall Herman Guring sells the
painting to a dealer in Amsterdam.
Here its trace is lost until it
reappears at the auction in New York 50
years later only to disappear from the
public eye once again.
But how did the potato eataters painter
become the famous Dr. Gashet painter?
How did Van Go progress from the dusty
earth colors to the garish contrasts?
The transformation takes place in Paris
in 1886 where Vincent Fang go finds the
style that makes him immortal as an
artist.
Vincent soaks up everything Europe's art
capital has to offer. Like here in the
Louv,
he had something like a photographic
memory. So when he would sit and study a
painting, which he could sometimes do
for as long as a day, he would remember
the passages of color uh brush work that
that created a kind of imaginary museum.
This insatiable thirst for art is only
one reason for his visit to Paris. Here,
Vincent is also reunited with his
brother, Teao, who lives in Paris as a
successful art dealer.
>> You're always welcome in Paris.
Come, let's go home.
>> Teao's monthly cash injections are
hardly enough for Vincent's artistic
ambitions. He is simply looking for a
cheap place to live and therefore wants
to move in with Teao.
Construction of the Eiffel Tower is just
beginning in Paris. Industrialization
changes the city and science changes the
way we look at the world. Photography
makes it possible to capture their
image. Classical painting faces serious
competition.
It is an overroought fatalistic time.
Lie de Labu. The desire for booze and
excess reigns in the city's cabarets and
cafes. Poets drinking themselves to
death and painters losing their minds
exert great fascination at the end of
the century. Vincent lives with his
younger brother in Paris for 2 years.
I'm back. Good. The art dealer brings
Vincent into contact with the Parisian
avantgard.
Painters whose works finally banish the
old-fashioned from Van Go's works.
Vincent, can you come here, please?
I was able to buy one of Tulus Latre's
paintings.
Portrai is the name of the portrait of
the young woman at the table. Vincent is
thrilled and at the same time inspired
to evolve the avonggard style even
further.
See here how the color draws the eye.
And now imagine the tablecloth blue
and the tin orange. How intensely that
would shine.
Gor Sa Louis Anat or Emil Bernard.
Vincent's new acquaintances have long
been experimenting with shapes and
colors, dots and surfaces.
Fungo wants to be like them, but here
too he remains an outsider.
He goes to the suarees of Tulus and uh
Susafon tells afterwards what this
consisted of. Simply a boy, a person who
came in with a canvas underneath his
arm, would sit in a corner, would say
nothing, and at the end of the uh the
suare he left again.
But Vincent also pushes ahead
enthusiastically with his painting on
his own. In no time at all, he masters
the stylistic devices of the avong
guard. He feverishly experiments with
the element that would retain the
greatest significance for him until the
end of his life, color.
With the help of woolen threads, he
tests contrasts with which he wants to
increase the intensity of his pictures.
It is the awakening of an exceptional
artist.
>> It's not that he abandons what he's done
in the Netherlands. He's um transforming
it, but he's keeping to the the very
pronounced brush strokes and his very
personal style.
>> His artistic transformation is made
clear by two self-portraits that Van
painted in Paris. The first was painted
shortly after his arrival and is still
in the old earth colors. The second he
paints shortly before his departure, a
self-confident artist in Van Go's famous
cobalt blue. However, his face also
shows signs of exhaustion.
In Paris, he got lost. It has something
to do with the stress indeed to to be
part of the oven at the time. And uh for
that reason he went to the south of
France and had a kind of idea that that
was paradise which of course it wasn't
but that's what he expected of it.
Vincent Fangar arrives in Province in
the spring of 1888.
It is the beginning of the two most
important years of his creative life.
In the meantime he has thrown off the
shackles of realistic portrayals. Here
he finally wants to paint things as he
sees them and feels them.
He wants to capture the truth, the
essence of things. And in doing so, he
breaks the boundaries of art at the
time.
Without regard for his health, he paints
everything he sees in front of his
canvas on a peacework basis.
180 paintings in just over a year. an
enormous legacy and a captivating style.
The sheer physicality of these paintings
and and the very bright vivid color
schemes and most of all the emotions
that this conveys, you really sense the
it's the feeling that he wanted to
convey.
The city of Ar and its surroundings are
now both the setting and the motif for
his work. This is where he takes up
residence. Are his aspirations now
fulfilled in Arl?
I think he remained the outsider. He he
was not part of the community in that
sense. I mean he was looked upon by the
people in the town. Who's this strange
artist wandering around?
>> Fan's cafe terrace in the evening is one
of the paintings created in Al. So
famous today that the cafe is one of the
main attractions for tourists visiting
Brace.
Just a few hundred meters further on on
plus lain is the no less famous yellow
house. Fangor rented it in the late
summer of 1888 and captured his new home
on canvas in glaring contrasts.
On the first floor, he furnishes his
bedroom. He paints it in colors that are
meant to convey peace and security to
the viewer. Not in the picture. 12
chairs that he buys as soon as he moves
in for all the artist colleagues who are
to work and live with him in Al.
>> His bedroom is the one on the left and
the one on the right is going to be
Goen's bedroom when he comes to stay
because Vincent had a plan. Wouldn't it
be great? I'm living in this house. I
love this little town. You can get
around. There's a million subjects that
we can paint. Why don't I create a
studio of the south?
>> An artist commune.
Van Go paints sunflowers in all
variations to express his joy at the
guests he hopes will soon arrive. He
finds it easier to communicate his
feelings with color than with words.
Probably the most famous of the
sunflower paintings can be admired today
in the Van Go Museum in Amsterdam. But
what did Vincent's welcome picture look
like when he painted it and the colors
had not yet faded?
After Charlotte Kaspers has completed
her analyses, she can finally begin to
repaint the masterpiece with the
scientifically reproduced original
colors. She knows from the artist's
correspondence that he planned his
paintings meticulously.
Contrary to the myth of the impulsive
mad genius, his works were well thought
out in the best sense, but he was
incapable of painting slowly.
With Van Go in general, he works often
spontaneous, but you can compare it with
sporting. When you run every day, you're
very very good in it. and also with the
the rhythm of his brush strokes and and
the the thickness of his paint. And
that's because he's doing it every day.
It has this spontaneity, but also this
organization in it. It's really
difficult to uh to mimic and it's very
unnatural to copy very secure with all
this research uh data a painting that
was um painted really quickly. So that's
that's always the
the tension.
I should paint that quick as well, but
then it would not be a reconstruction of
his painting. Then it would be my
painting.
When somebody stands behind me and looks
at the painting, uh I feel very
vulnerable. I feel like um they think
that I'm exaggerating whereas I I'm
using the same pigments
>> to see the world through Van Go's eyes.
Thanks to Shalotta Kasper's
reconstruction, we can experience this
impression 130 years later.
This is what the sunflowers look like
today.
And this is how they might have looked
when the painting was still wet on
Vanguard's easel before the red faded
and the yellow discolored.
For me it was an important moment. Yeah.
suddenly thought, okay, this is this is
for religion because the color that you
see there is indeed so fresh, so so
colorful that you indeed get uh well
you you're glad
I feel what I paint. I paint what I
feel. Van Go once wrote when he painted
the sunflowers in Al. He must have been
very happy
and full of anticipation. The painter
Paul Gugger confirms his arrival.
Finally, a brother in spirit with whom
he hopes to share life and art. But in
expectation of his guest, Vincent works
even harder and faster. In anticipation,
he tires and burns himself out
recklessly.
When you look at how he worked, how
immensely productive he was, he was
almost working day and night uh on
paintings. Uh he was not eating well, he
was drinking too much. I mean, he did do
a lot of harm to his his health.
Before Goan came, he actually wrote that
he was so tired that he had to sleep for
2 days and uh take some rest. um which
he didn't want to because he wanted to
do all these paintings.
>> For the eagerly awaited guest, the
famous sunflowers, they were actually
created as wall decoration for Paul
Gogan's room.
What happens next is still the subject
of much speculation today. The author
Benedict Murphy has painstakingly
reconstructed what exactly happened in
the yellow house in the autumn of 1888
on the basis of countless documents in
the Altown archives.
Vincent's idea of an artist's commune
was to come to a dramatic end shortly
after Guggan's arrival in a
an undernourished and overexited yet
highly ambitious Van Go and the
self-confident Gul. Two exceptional
artists but also two excessive
characters in a confined space that
could not go well for long.
Finally, things start to go a little bit
strange towards the end of the month,
November. The weather is changing. They
can't go out and paint quite so much.
They just they start arguing about
pretty much everything.
Do I really seem like that to you?
Like a monkey with a paintbrush?
At the beginning uh when Goger came he
was I tend to think a little bit more
friendly to Goger uh in the terms of
well eager to learn something from Goer
but at the end of the stay of Go he
certainly tried to do and to show um Go
what he was capable of doing.
>> The true artist creates paintings from
his imagination from his memory.
>> Have you still not understood it? I want
to see the truth of things and then I
want to capture it on canvas. The
quarrels continue to escalate until the
day before Christmas Eve.
>> Just because you campaign for memory
doesn't mean all the other artists in
the world have to do without.
>> I only recognize what is true when I see
it in front of me. I can't just make it
up and then that is a lie. You're lying
to the viewer. Man,
>> and the reality of your sunflowers is a
color that makes you go blind.
After this dispute, Gogan probably
wanted to turn his back on Van Go for
good.
>> Van Gogh was just ruined by this because
he had worked so hard to create a little
community of artists. He had finally
gotten Goan to come down and live with
him. And deep down, I think he
understood that he would never be able
to live with anybody.
>> Vincent's really showing more and more
signs of disturbance. I'm going to tell
you what I've concluded to try and
understand what happened. Sometime after
dinner, Goang goes into the park.
In his memoirs written many years later,
Goger claims that Van Go threatened him
with a gun in a
cutthroat razor. and he was sufficiently
scared and Vincent returns to the yellow
house.
Gorgan does not follow him. Instead, he
spends the night in a hotel.
Meanwhile, the drama unfolds in the
yellow house. That night, with the very
razor he had previously wielded to
threaten Gogan, Van Go inflicts a
serious injury to his own ear.
He made a summery bandage out of rags
and then walks the 5 minutes to the
house of tolerance number one.
>> The street where the brothel was located
still looks the same today.
So, here we are now in R Jubul.
Unfortunately, the House of tolerance
number one no longer exists.
It was on the corner here just behind my
back. You'll um you can see that there's
cars parked here now, but the walls are
still there. Vincent Van Go came here,
walked up the street. He must have seen
a light on the corner. It was the most
prominent of all the brothel.
What happens next was reported to
Ajandam shortly afterwards by
eyewitnesses at the brothel.
Later, the mysterious events even end up
in the local newspaper.
Can you fetch Rachel, please?
>> Rachel.
Take good care of it, please.
>> Give it to me.
>> Until his death, Van Go remained silent
about what moved him to harm himself so
severely. But he did process this event
in his paintings
in the dormatory of the asylum in Ald
for example. The asylum where Vincent
was taken the next day after a policeman
found him unconscious at home
and in self-portrait with a bandage.
But what actually happened? What exactly
did Van Go do to himself that night?
In the course of her research, Bernardet
Murphy also comes across a document in
the archives of the University of
Berkeley that could solve this more than
130year-old mystery. It was made by one
of the few people who saw Van Go's
injury. His doctor in a
>> was a dream document to find. It's just
a ripped off piece of paper from a
doctor's prescription form and it's
dated 1930,
18th of August 1930. It says the ear was
cut with a razor
>> and the doctor even describes how Van Go
must have proceeded.
>> Vincent pulled up his ear, took a razor,
and sliced through his ear.
And then it says what the ear looked
like
afterwards.
And then he gives a little thing. He
says, "I'm very happy to give you this
uh testimony about my unhappy friend."
And he signs it Dr. Ray.
A few months after this fit, Vincent
moves at his own request from Al to the
mental asylum in Simi, 30 km away.
His mental and spiritual state unsettles
him. Taking care of himself costs him
too much energy.
Above all, Vincent wants to justify
Teao's trust and finally find success.
And to do that, he has to keep painting
against all odds. He is now 36 years
old. In his 9 years as an artist, he has
not managed to stand on his own two feet
financially.
>> Yeah.
>> Your brother has sent a partner.
>> Ah, finally.
I sent him a list 3 weeks ago with all
the colors that I urgently need. My
brushes have all lost their hair.
Thank you,
Teao. now married still sends him
paints, brushes and canvases regularly.
These utensils are more important than
medicine for the restless artist,
artist's lifeline during this agonizing
period.
When he is afflicted by fits, he is
unable to paint. But in the phases in
between, Van Go continues to create
masterpieces such as the famous Starry
Night.
In this fantasy landscape, he makes us
the world outside his window with
memories and feelings in a grandiose
pictorial symbiosis.
The swirls of clouds and stars in
particular stand out with their
undulating lines. Some art historians
see in them the expression of inner
ecstatic states which according to Van
Go in his letters the sight of nature
always triggered in him. At the same
time however the stars also seem to have
been a source of comfort and hope for
him.
>> At one point he actually says in his
letters when I have a feel for something
for for religion
I go out and paint the stars.
In the center of the picture, Van Go has
even hidden a wistful memory of his
childhood. Church steeples like this are
not to be found in Proce, but they are
in his Dutch homeland.
Today, it is difficult to know for sure
what demons tormented the patient
Vincent Van.
At the time, the director of the
institution in Sari believed it to be
epilepsy with delusional ideas. It was
to remain unchallenged as the sole
diagnosis.
Knowledge about mental illness was
limited at the time and the only
therapy, regular baths, does not help
Vincent either.
After a year, he finally gives up his
confinement experiment and turns his
back on the south of France.
He realizes, of course, that he has to
go through society to become better. He
needs people around him. I mean, he's
living amidst patience. Come on, that
doesn't help you.
In the summer resort town of Ouris,
north of Paris, Vincent Fang tries one
last time to stand on his own two feet.
Here in the Ober Ravu, he lives cheaply
and all alone.
Several times he tries to lure Teao and
his wife Johanna to visit, but this last
attempt to find a family also fails.
Instead, a terrible quarrel breaks out
in Paris between the brothers who are
always very close.
During this time, Vincent is under the
medical care of Dr. Gashier, the man
whose portrait will later fetch a record
price. But Dr. Gashier will no longer be
able to help Vincent.
A few days after the confrontation with
Teao on the 27th of July 1890, Vincent
Fang goes to the fields behind the
church of OA.
There he tries to take his own life with
a revolver.
Badly injured, the painter drags himself
back to the orbe.
The doctor who is summoned cannot save
Vincent Van.
Teao has rushed from Paris and sits in
the chair next to him. Vincent dies 2
days later, aged only 37.
It's clear that he was not hopeful for
the future, that he had a lot of
worries, that he was depressed. Um, the
fact that he didn't want to be a burden
for Teao anymore was probably part of
it. But, um, but there's no there
there's not one reason, I think, uh, why
he decided to to end his life.
The painter is buried in the aair
cemetery.
His brother Teao only lives half a year
longer. He dies of syphilis.
The artist and his brother Patron rest
side by side to this day.
Vincent Van Go painted 90 paintings in
the 70 days he spent in OA.
One of the last, a kind of legacy, wheat
field with crows.
Vincent wrote to his brother that he
wanted to express sadness and extreme
loneliness with this painting, but also
the vitality, the force of nature which
fascinated him throughout his life.
The myth of the mad painter claims Van
Go painted like this because he was
crazy.
His
letters and his art paint a different
picture. Van Go painted in this way
because his soul was so fragile, his
sensibility so vulnerable, and his art
was perhaps his only gateway to life.
Even painting could not save Vincent Van
Go in the end, but it made him immortal.
His life has moved and influenced
millions of people. His example has
freed artists all over the world from
the constraints of realism and
encouraged them to experiment freely
with colors and form.
He became an example for every artist.
If you want to achieve something and you
have a girl, please try it, do it. And
knowing that certain risks were involved
because you could fail, because you
could not sell, because you could poor.
But if she believes in it, hey, try it.
>> There's a sentence in his many letters
in which he says, "Nothing could make me
happier than that the average person
would hang my paintings on their walls."
His wish actually came true. With his
paintings, he succeeded in connecting
with the souls of people all over the
world. This gave Vincent Van Go the
companionship that was denied him
throughout his life.